Okay, so picking it up from the Mishna on דף נ"ב עמוד
ב'. Daf Nun Bet Amud Bet.
So, המטמא והמדמע והמנסך, HaMetameh VeHaMedameh VeHaMenasech,
בשוגג פטור במזיד חייב. beshogeg patur bemeizid chayav. So now we get
to a new תיקון עולם, tikkun olam, something that takes us—we dealt
with the whole thing about collecting debt, then we are, this פרק
perek is much more financial, at least that's the way it's been
so far. Then we got into this whole interesting thing about orphans
and people that are
אפוטרופסים, apotropsim, guardians and so on for their financial doings. And now
we get to נזק. nezek. So, someone goes ahead and does an
act of damage, but as the גמרא Gemara is going to characterize
this, this is היזק שאינו ניכר. hezek she'eino nikar. This is a
damage that is not visible, invisible damage. So, it's like they say,
what do they say about somebody that believes in God? He has
an invisible means of support.
So anyway, okay, but anyway, so this is invisible damage. So what
is it? You are מטמא, metameh, you go ahead and throw, let's
say you touch, you're טמא tameh or you take a שרץ, sheretz,
a dead rodent, and you put it—touch it to somebody's grain. Maybe
it's even תרומה terumah grain. And now the grain is going from
being able to be eaten by כהנים, Kohanim, all you can do
right now with it is burn it. What you can do with
טמא תרומה tamei terumah is benefit from it as it's burning, okay?
So it's obviously worth a lot less. But if somebody looks at
it, they don't see anything different.
מדמע Medameh is you take somebody—separated out תרומה terumah and they have
a תרומה terumah pile and they have their חולין chullin pile, and
you go and you mix it all together. So somebody looks at
it, it just looks like a big pile of grain. What did
I do? I just mixed some grain together. But the reality is
is that now, until now, their חולין chullin was worth $10 a
pound, and their תרומה terumah was worth $5 a pound, because only
כהנים Kohanim could eat the תרומה. terumah. Now that it's all mixed
up, it all effectively can only be eaten by כהנים, Kohanim, so
now it's all only worth like $5 a pound, right? But you
can't see that damage. It's not visible. That's what happens when you
live in a Halachic world. You can have damage that isn't visible
and serious, right?
So, okay. ומנסך u-menasech is you go ahead and you take somebody's
wine and you do a libation to עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So
the גמרא Gemara is going to say, well, that's a little worse
than just damages, what about for that's like a huge transgression. But
anyway, we'll get to that. But anyway, now the wine is אסור
בהנאה, assur be-hana'ah, even though there's nothing visible about it. So in
all those cases, בשוגג פטור, beshogeg patur, if that was accidental—how exactly
you're מנסך menasech wine to עבודה זרה avoda zara accidentally I don't
know, but anyway—במזיד חייב, bemeizid chayav, if it's intentional, you are obligated.
So the question is, which way does the תיקון עולם tikkun olam
go? Does because normal damage you're חייב chayav whether you're בשוגג beshogeg
or במזיד. bemeizid. So is the default here that is the עיקר
הדין ikar hadin that you should be חייב chayav and the תיקון
עולם tikkun olam was to get you off the hook when you're
בשוגג? beshogeg? Why did that be? That doesn't make sense, why should
we get you off the hook? But or we'll see in the
גמרא, Gemara, that's one opinion. The other opinion is that the עיקר
הדין ikar hadin is that you're פטור patur and the תיקון עולם
tikkun olam is we gotta make you pay, or else you're gonna
get away with willfully damaging somebody else's property. So let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. Before it gets to the core issue
in the משנה, Mishna, which is what is the nature of היזק
שאינו ניכר hezek she'eino nikar and whether מעיקר הדין me'ikar hadin you're
חייב chayav or פטור, patur, the גמרא Gemara at first wanted to
address the particular cases. איתמר, itmar, it was taught, מנסך. menasech. רב
Rav says מנסך ממש, menasech mamash, Rav says literally it means to
pour the wine to עבודה זרה. avoda zara. ושמואל אמר מערב. u-Shmuel
amar me'arev. No, what you do is you take יין של עבודה
זרה yayin shel avoda zara that's been poured by a Jew or
a non-Jew, it doesn't really matter, and you go ahead and you
mix it in with kosher wine. Sort of like מדמע. medameh. You
didn't actually go ahead and change its status, but you mixed it
in with kosher wine. מאן דאמר מערב מאי טעמא לא אמר מנסך?
man de'amar me'arev mai ta'ama lo amar menasech? The one that says
it talks about mixing it, why does he not say it's talking
about anointing it? אמר לך מנסך קים ליה בדרבה מיניה. amar lach
menasech kam leih biderabbah mineih. Because if you do ניסוך, nisuch, then
you're חייב ניסוך chayav nisuch when you pour wine, do a libation
to עבודה זרה. avoda zara. And therefore, if you're חייב ניסוך, chayav
nisuch, that overrides any monetary payment. That's called קים ליה בדרבה מיניה,
kam leih biderabbah mineih, we establish him with the greater punishment. So
if somebody does a—two in one act and that act has in
it both a capital crime and a monetary payment aspect, we say
the capital crime overwhelms or overshadows any monetary thing that he
is doing, and therefore he does not have to pay for any
monetary obligation that he incurs at that time. Now, this can be
in two scenarios. One could be that if we're actually giving you
the harsher punishment, we're not going to also make you pay financially.
If we're executing somebody, we're not also going to make him pay
for damages that were incurred at the time. That you find in
when the person is getting sometimes like lashes, מלקות. malkus. That's the
principle called אין אדם לוקה ומשלם. ein adam lokeh u-meshalem. We don't
give you lashes and make you pay.
We're only going to—we're only going to actually exact one punishment for
one act, okay? Then there's all these questions about what does it
mean one act? Like let's say, here I am, I'm eating חזיר
chazir with my mouth and I'm stomping on your vessels—yeah,
and I'm breaking—and I'm breaking your vase with my other hand. Is
that because it's the same time? Or... is it only how do
you exactly define—and it's your חזיר chazer that I'm eating, right? So
maybe that is one act, right? But anyway, but if it's defined
as one act, I'm not going to give you two punishments. I
got to decide which punishment I'm going to give you and I'm
going to give you the harsher one, I'm going to give you
the מלקות, malkos, קים ליה בדרבה מיניה. Kam lei b'darba minei. But
קים ליה בדרבה מיניה Kam lei b'darba minei is different. קים ליה
בדרבה מיניה Kam lei b'darba minei is even if we're not punishing
you. There were not witnesses, there was not התראה, hasra'ah, it's not
a time where there's a בית דין Beis Din that does executions,
that punishes for capital crimes. The very fact that you did such
a weighty
עבירה aveira overshadows the significance of anything else that you did in
that context. Anything else that you did is like trivial. Here you
were, you did an act of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, like I
can't even think about the fact that you damaged somebody's property. That's
completely
irrelevant in the context of the horrific nature, sort of religiously horrific
nature of this act. So that's the principle of קים ליה בדרבה
מיניה. Kam lei b'darba minei. So how could there be any financial
liability in that case? So that's his question.
אידך, Idach, the other one says back, כדרבי ירמיה, k'de-Rabbi Yirmiya, like
רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya says. אמר רבי ירמיה, Amar Rabbi Yirmiya, משעת
הגבהה הוא דקנה. mishas hagbah hu dekana. No,
cause this is a question about defining what is the same act.
When you lifted up the bottle of wine to pour it, that
was your act of stealing, that was your act of being חייב
chayav in damages. מתחייב בנפשו לא הוי עד שעת ניסוך. mischayav b'nafsho
lo havi ad sha'as nisuch.
You're not obligated for קים ליה בדרבה מיניה, Kam lei b'darba minei,
you're not obligated for acts of עבודה זרה avodah zarah until you
actually do the libation. Now, there's a little bit of a problem
with that if you realize it because lifting it up could be
an act of גניבה, gneivah, an act of theft. But if it's
an act of theft, it's not the case in the משנה Mishna
about היזק שאינו ניכר. hezek she'eino nikar. The damage was not the
act that it's poured לעבודה זרה l'avodah zarah and it's אסור בהנאה.
assur behana'ah. The point that you're חייב chayav is because you stole
it. So then it's just a standard obligation for stealing something, right?
Is that clear? Meaning the cases in the משנה Mishna are unique
in that you did an act of damaging, but it's not a
visible damage. If this is saying that you actually poured it לעבודה
זרה, l'avodah zarah, but you're חייב chayav because from the moment you
pick it up because then at that moment let's say you stole
it, even though you haven't made it אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, you
haven't made it יין נסך, yayin nesech, but then it's just a
case of גניבה gneivah or גזילה, gzeilah, right? It's not a case
of היזק שאינו ניכר. hezek she'eino nikar.
But if it's מנסך, menasech, of course it's היזק שאינו ניכר hezek
she'eino nikar no matter
what because there's—you'll see there's less wine in there, so it is
ניכר. nikar.
Oh, no. You could pour it from one vessel into the next.
רש״י Rashi says you could do מנסך menasech by just moving your
hand and swishing your hand around. But then you don't have the
case about picking it up. Okay, but anyway. No, no, no. But
you pour from one vessel to the next or you pour it
back or something of that nature. Okay.
קל וחומר, Kal vachomer, if you want to punish somebody for something,
you use their greater punishment. Right. Why should the person who was
damaged be out of that? I mean, why shouldn't you have to
pay him and then you get killed?
I understand. So that's
the—and sometimes the גמרא Gemara sort of discusses that. There's a whole
סוגיא sugya about מיתה לזה וממון לזה. misa le-zeh u-mamon le-zeh. Is
there a way of somehow separating those two acts? Yeah, I understand.
I mean, it's not fair to the person who's damaged. That's true.
But okay, so anyway, but if you take a look—so you understand
my question? If you say look at רש״י, Rashi, right? דהגבהה, De-hagbah,
רש״י Rashi says אמנת לגזלו. amnat legazlo. But according to that explanation,
if the משנה Mishna is talking about ניסוך nisuch and you can't
be חייב chayav for ניסוך nisuch because of קים ליה Kam lei
and you're חייב chayav for picking it up, then it's a case
of גזילה. gzeilah. So it's not a case of היזק שאינו ניכר,
hezek she'eino nikar, right? If I steal and then I'm חייב chayav
whether it's שוגג shogeg or מזיד, meizid, it's גזילה. gzeilah. So if
you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says קים ליה בדרבה מיניה.
Kam lei b'darba minei.
So תוספות Tosafot says like this,
it's one, two, three, like five lines from the bottom. Okay. Do
people have that?
Where are you starting from?
Five lines from the bottom of the דף, daf, at the end
of the line.
ויש לומר דסבר שמואל דהגבהה צורך ניסוך הוא. V'yesh lomar d'savar Shmuel
de-hagbah tzorech nisuch hu. Okay. די אפשר לנסך בלא הגבהה. D'i efshar
lenasech belo hagbah. So what תוספות Tosafot is saying— I know, so
רש״י—this Rashi is the conversation we're having in ברכות Brachos when they're
talking about it's like exactly the same— Which case? Of the thief
stealing on שבת, Shabbos, a purse from a house.
Oh, right, right, exactly. You couldn't have carried it
out if you didn't pick it up. You couldn't have shot the
arrow, you couldn't have torn the
silk if you didn't shoot the arrow. Exactly. So this is תוספות
Tosafot is saying. So, you know, he says the act of היזק—but
hezek it's interesting, the act of—where do we define the act
of ניסוך nisuch beginning in terms of your חייב מיתה? chayav mita.
That was from the moment you poured it. When do we define
the act of ניסוך nisuch beginning when we're looking at it through
the lens of not הלכות עבודה זרה, hilchos avodah zarah, but when
we're looking at it at the lens of through הלכות נזק? hilchos
nezek? When did the damage begin? The process of damaging began as
soon as I took your wine with the intention of doing... something
wrong to it, right? I'm invading your property and this is beginning
the process of damage. I'm still חייב chayav not for גזילה, gezeila,
I'm חייב chayav for damage, but the damaging process began at this
moment. The act of עבודה זרה avodah zarah begins only when I
actually do the pouring. So תוספות Tosafos says it's not גזילה, gezeila,
there's both נזק nezek and עבודה זרה avodah zarah going on here.
The נזק nezek process starts a little bit earlier and therefore you
could—it's not קים ליה בדרבה מיניה. kimlei b'derabbah minei. Alright, so that's
שמואל's Shmuel position.
Okay.
ולמאן דאמר—now u'l'man d'amar the גמרא Gemara says like this—ולמאן דאמר מנסך,
u'l'man d'amar m'nasech, מאי טעמא לא אמר מערב? mai ta'ama lo amar
m'arev? So if you say it's a case of actually pouring wine
to עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, which gets complicated, why didn't we say
קים ליה kimlei and you have to separate which, you know, when
the moments that the two acts begin? So why not just say
that it's talking about mixing up the wine? So you could say
well because the משנה Mishna says מנסך. m'nasech. But anyway, אמר לך—מערב,
היינו מדמע. hainu m'dama. He says besides that's the simple meaning of
the word, but then it's not a new חידוש chiddush from the
case of mixing תרומה terumah with חולין chullin grain. So if you
told me mixing תרומה terumah grain with חולין chullin grain is a
case, then obviously mixing יין נסך yayin nesech with other wine is
a case. I mean there it's conceptually the same.
I mean there it's conceptual. In one case you can give it
to the כהנים, Kohanim, and here you can't do anything.
Okay, well the גמרא Gemara will get to that. That's possible. Okay,
so that's a possible difference. So we'll see about that. ואידך—the v'idach
other one will say—קנסא הוא. k'nasa hu. Before you even try to
explain why this is more חידוש chiddush than the next one, he
says look, all of these things are
קנסות—ומקנסא לא ילפינן. And because חז״ל Chazal decided to make a קנס
k'nas in one case, you cannot decide that by logic that the
same type of logic should apply in another case. Okay, because קנס
k'nas is not the same as damages. So this number one establishes
the idea that מעיקר הדין me'ikar hadin you should be פטור patur
in all these cases. It's היזק שאינו ניכר. hezek she'eino nikar. But
the other חידוש chiddush is קנס. k'nas. Even if we say מעיקר
הדין me'ikar hadin you should be פטור, patur, right, when חז״ל Chazal
are going to say but we're going to have to make you
pay anyway. Like why do you think חז״ל Chazal would say, just
to anticipate the גמרא—היזק
שאינו ניכר She'eino Nikar, you're really פטור. patur. We're going to make
you pay anyway if you did it במזיד. b'meizid. What do you
think the reason would be?
To prevent
people
from...
Yeah, to prevent people—giving people an option that you can intentionally do
something that—the guy you don't like, you can go ahead and damage
their stuff and get away with it, right? שלא יהא כל אחד
הולך ומטמא טהרותיו של חבירו ואומר פטור אני. shelo yehei kol echad
holech u'metamei taharosav shel chaveiro v'omer patur ani. The גמרא's Gemara going
to say. Now, because to close off that we're going to say
you're going to have to pay when you're—when you're במזיד. b'meizid. So
when we're making you pay because you're במזיד, b'meizid, would you say
the nature of that payment is a קנס? k'nas? A קנס k'nas
means it's a form of monetary punishment. Is that what we're doing?
We're punishing you? Right, I wouldn't call it a קנס, k'nas, I
would actually call it that they're like instituting a new category of
compensation. Like, alright, are we—or you could say no, it is about
punishing you or smacking you, but it's smacking you, you know, for
the sake of social control. That actually is a certain degree of
a קנס. k'nas. But I would actually say what we're doing is
we're closing a gap. There's a gap here in the system that
it's unjust that somebody could be willful—a person could do willful damage
and the other person not get compensated. So I would say that
it's a type of a rabbinic תשלומים. tashlumim. It's not a rabbinic
קנס. k'nas. So I think that's an interesting question. You know, maybe
the language of so you shouldn't be able to get away with
it focuses us on that idea of punishment. We're punishing you or
we're giving you a disincentive. And that's what's making the גמרא Gemara
think about it as a קנס. k'nas. You could have taken the
same thing and thought about it the other way. It's not fair
that this guy should suffer for a willful act of damage that
was done to him. So therefore we have to allow him to
be compensated. But you're right, because the גמרא Gemara focuses on stopping
you from doing this act, it sees it as a type of
a קנס. k'nas. And if it is a type of a קנס,
k'nas, well you know, you cannot necessarily logically equate cases. If it's
a type of compensation, we could say if somebody lost as a
result of somebody else's willful act, they deserve to get paid. Well
then that would apply to—like logically to all cases, you know, that
are in that category. But if it's an issue of social control
or punishment, maybe there's different psychologies and realities and so on that
in some cases demand more social control or demand more punishment than
others. Some cases are more common than others. Some cases there's more
of a temptation than others. Right, so maybe we can't always identify—assume
just because you make a קנס k'nas in one case you're going
to make a קנס k'nas in another case. Okay, so that's the
odd logic of the גמרא. Gemara What do you want to say
Jenna? So it seems weird, right? But let's say it's like you
know one in a million somebody mixes up wine of יין נסך.
yayin nesech. Like יין נסך yayin nesech never happens. This other issue
about grain of תרומה, terumah, like every single day people, you know
every harvest season people are dealing with תרומה terumah and keeping separate
piles and whatever, and it's a much bigger issue. So there we
have to institute certain types of controls that we don't in the
other case. So if it's a תשלומים tashlumim you could make a
comparison. If it's קנס k'nas you can't. Yes.
Two questions. The one is, so היזק שאינו ניכר hezek she'eino nikar
has to mean like—not necessarily externally visible but just for instance, like
if I make an animal טרפה, treifah, looks the same, essentially. Does
that—but that wouldn't be היזק שאינו ניכר, hezek she'eino nikar would it?
No, because you could see that it's a טרפה. treifah.
I mean I can't.
Well, if you opened it up you could see. Yeah.
So then the other question is, how do we—I mean, how do
we know that it's not...
But we'll see. We're going to get to it in the גמרא.
Gemara. Okay, so let's look at רש"י. Rashi. דקנסו דקנסו לא יפקינן.
de'knasu de'knasu lo yafkinan. That's רש"י Rashi in the second narrow line.
דהא למדינהו. de'ha lamdinhu.
It's not like a real law, like it's תשלומין tashlumin or something,
some sense of justice. דהיכא דקנס קנס והיכא דלא
קנס לא קנס. de'heicha de'knas knas ve'heicha de'lo knas lo knas. Whatever
they did they did. Now רש"י Rashi doesn't say why. It makes
it sound arbitrary. But the point is, anyway, the point is if
it's about, as Michael said nicely, social control or punishment, some cases
need that more than other cases. Okay, so that's why he says
that we have to say both cases. Okay, so what we have
here is an interesting debate about what the case is and the
reading of קים ליה בדרבה מיניה, kim lei b'deraba minei, but the
more interesting thing is how to characterize what's going on in the
משנה. Mishna. And the גמרא Gemara. here has implicitly characterized it, or
explicitly, as קנס, knas, fundamentally a פטור pattur and a type of
a קנס. knas. So let's take a look. Now
the גמרא Gemara says: ולמאן דאמר קנסא מקנסא—and u'le'man de'amar knasa mi'knasa
one says that—ולמאן דיליף קנסא מקנסא, u'le'man de'yalif knasa mi'knasa, the one
who says that actually the reason it's מנסך menasech is because had
it just been mixing the wine I would have learned out from
the case of מדמע. medamea. So that's saying that you can learn
out from one case of קנס knas to another
case of קנס. knas. So כל הני למה לי, kol hanei lama
li, so why did you need all three cases in the משנה?
Mishna? Why couldn't I have just said one and inferred the other?
Right? You get it? If according to שמואל Shmuel that says that
you could have learned out mixing wine from the case of mixing
תרומה, terumah, and therefore he understood the case of wine to be
pouring wine—well if that's true, then he's saying you can learn one
case of קנס knas from another. So why do you need all
three cases? So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: No, צריכא, tzricha, you need all three. דאי תנא מטמא, de'i
tana metamei, if it had just said impurifying the grain, אי תרומה
הויא, ei terumah havya, let's say the grain was תרומה, terumah, so
הוי אמינא משום דקא מפסדי ליה לגמרי hava amina mishum de'ka mafsadei
lei l'gamrei because that's a very significant loss, לגמרי, l'gamrei, not totally
לגמרי, l'gamrei, but it goes from stuff that could be eaten to
stuff that can just be burnt. So it's basically, it's almost a
complete loss. So הוי אמינא משום דקא מפסדי ליה לגמרי. hava amina
mishum de'ka mafsadei lei l'gamrei. So therefore that I would have said,
those are cases you have to pay, but not cases where it's
only a relative loss. ואי מטמא חולין, ve'ei metamei chullin, and if
the case was not תרומה terumah but חולין, chullin, and חולין chullin
by the way, חולין טמא chullin tamei is not worth so much
less than חולין טהור. chullin tahor. There are some people that only
eat חולין טהור, chullin tahor, but for most people it's the exact
same, so the actual loss is very small. So if you tell
me even a small loss, shouldn't I be able to figure out
every other case from that? No. That's special. Why is that
special? משום דאסור לגרום טומאה לחולין שבארץ ישראל mishum de'asur ligrom tumah
l'chullin she'be'eretz yisrael because there, in addition to the נזק nezek that
you did to your fellow person, you also transgressed a ritual sin.
You caused חולין chullin to become טמא, tamei, and you can't even
cause חולין chullin to become טמא tamei in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Okay, so because of the extra ritual sin maybe we would fine
you. So that case could not—you could not have inferred all other
cases. Either it was an almost complete loss and you couldn't have
applied it to cases where it was a partial loss, or there
was an additional ritual sin that was going on there.
There's a difference of a זוז zuz between חולין טמא chullin tamei
and חולין טהור, chullin tahor,
which is very small.
Okay, but nevertheless, maybe it's specifically because there was something else additionally
problematic with that act. Okay, so I couldn't have inferred other cases.
Now, ואי אשמעינן מדמע, ve'ei ashmi'inan medamea, now how about mixing תרומה
terumah with חולין? chullin? As you see, that has neither of those
two features. It's not totally valueless now. It went down from ten
dollars a bushel to five dollars a bushel because now only כהנים
kohanim can eat it. But you haven't made it totally valueless. You
haven't technically done a sin. Okay, so that case I couldn't have
learned from that to this. Now why not just tell me the
case of mixing? ואי אשמעינן מדמע ve'ei ashmi'inan medamea משום דשכיח mishum
de'shchiach
because that's maybe a very common occurrence. Like I said, you have
a pile when you're separating out תרומה, terumah, you've got your תרומה
terumah pile and your חולין chullin pile. And maybe it's very easy
to mix those two together. Okay, and that would be something that
we have to really protect against.
אבל מטמא דלא שכיח, aval metamei de'lo shchiach, but to go ahead
and cause טומאה, tumah, which is not—it's so funny when we learn
about טומאה וטהרה tumah ve'taharah we think that everybody is טמא tamei
left and right. But anyway, but I still think it's a little
different as opposed to people keep their—whatever. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara thinks
that that's less common. Okay, maybe in a world where there was
a lot of טומאה tumah people were very careful about it. אימא
לא, eima lo, maybe we wouldn't—so maybe there's a question also about
how prevalent it is, how big of a loss, how prevalent, how
much other violations did you do in the process. All of these
are relevant factors. ואי אשמעינן מטמא ומדמע, ve'ei ashmi'inan metamei u'medamea, if
it had
just told us those two, משום דלא קים ליה בדרבה מיניה. mishum
de'lo kim lei b'deraba minei. So fine, those are normal cases. You
don't have this special idea of קים ליה. kim lei. אבל מנסך
דקים ליה בדרבה מיניה, aval menasech de'kim lei b'deraba minei, I would
have thought that pouring it to עבודה זרה, avoda zara, there's a
special exemption because you're חייב chayav מיתה. misa? So אימא לא, eima
lo, קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, so this teaches us כדרבי
ירמיה, ke'de'rabbi yirmiyah, like what רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah said, that the
process began when you picked it up and therefore you don't say
קים ליה. kim lei. So each one of these needed to be
said. In principle you could learn out from one case to another
if all the parameters are the same, but the parameters weren't the
same and therefore we needed each one of these three cases. So
now the גמרא Gemara says: ולהא דתני אבוה דרבי אבין בראשונה היו
אומרים. u'le'ha de'tani avuh de'rabbi avin barishona hayu omrim.
We have a ברייתא braisa that says the following, originally they used
to say המטמא והמנסך, hametamei ve'hamenasech, it was only cases of טומאה
tumah and pouring the wine. חזרו לומר אף המדמע Chazru lomar af
hamidame'a and then they applied it even to the case of mixing.
So כל הני למה לי? kol hanei lama li? Why do you
need all those? By the way, that also shows that it's a
case of a fine and not a case of like instituting a
rabbinic type of a נזק, nezek, because if it was a rabbinic
נזק, nezek, right, you would not have, you know, said well we're
only we only need to do it these two cases. Oh now
we realized there's a third thing that the problem we have to
apply it to the third. It makes it seem very clearly that
we're identifying certain problems that are existing in the society and we're
coming and addressing them, not that we're creating a new category of
rabbinic נזק. nezek. And the question here of the גמרא Gemara is
that this shows you that that מדמע midame'a is like the the
biggest חידוש, chiddush, the last thing I would have said. Right first
I would have done מטמא metamei and מנסך menasech before מדמע. midame'a.
Why is that? What's the logic of that progression? So כל הני
למה לי? kol hanei lama li? צריכא, tzricha, you need it. אי
אשמעינן מטמא, Ee ashmeinan metamei, had it just started with טומאה, tumah,
משום דלא קים ליה בדרבה מיניה, mishum delo kam lei biderabba minei,
obviously there's no special exemption of קים ליה. kam lei. אבל מנסך,
Aval menasech, דקים ליה בדרבה מיניה, de'kam lei biderabba minei, אימא לא,
eima lo, but I might have thought that by pouring to עבודה
זרה avodah zarah you're exempt because of קים ליה. kam lei. ואי
אשמעינן מנסך, Ve'ee ashmeinan menasech, had it said מנסך, menasech, משום דקא
מפסיד ליה לגמרי, mishum deka mafsid lei legamrei, when you pour the
wine it's now ממש mamash as Michael pointed out literally worthless, right?
It's אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. So אבל מטמא, aval metamei, when you're
מטמא, metamei, even if you're מטמא תרומה, metamei terumah, דלא מפסיד ליה
לגמרי, delo mafsid lei legamrei, it's not it's not totally worthless. Even
תרומה טמאה terumah temei'ah you could still use as fuel, as firewood,
you could still burn it. אימא לא, Eima lo, so maybe in
that case they won't. So when you have the two of them
combined, you see we don't the קים ליה kam lei isn't a
problem because the process starts earlier. And you see that you still
pay, but you're only paying in both of those cases because the
loss is almost complete. In מנסך menasech it's a hundred percent loss
and in תרומה טמאה terumah temei'ah it's a ninety-five percent loss. Okay?
But it's a heavy loss. ואי אשמעינן הני תרתי, Ve'ee ashmeinan hanei
tarti, but if I only had those two, משום דהפסד מרובה, mishum
de'hefsed merubeh, because it's almost a complete loss. אבל מדמע, Aval midame'a,
when you're mixing תרומה terumah and חולין, chullin, maybe it's only a
fifty percent loss in that case, maybe it's only a thirty percent
loss, because כהנים kohanim can still eat it, right? דהפסד מועט, De'hefsed
muat, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe we that didn't need us to,
you know, go ahead and exert this type of a punishment and
a fine and so on. You know, it's not as big of
a problem. צריכא, Tzricha, so you need to tell me all three
cases. So this is nice, it it it highlights the different things
that would have motivated me in one case as opposed to the
other, but more particularly what it highlights is the fact that it's
a קנס. knas. And the fact that it's a קנס knas means
number one that in principle you should be totally exempt, and number
two that the reason we're making you pay is not out of
any רחמנות rachmanus for the damagee, the ניזק, nezak, that he deserves
compensation, but it's out of the fact that we have to control
and and you know these types of activities. We have to punish
you after the fact or what it sounds more from the גמרא
Gemara rather than punishing after the fact is as Michael said which
is what you normally think of קנס knas is what Michael said
about social control. We have to disentivize people from the outset. Okay,
but the degree depending on how big of a problem it is,
how prevalent it is, how much of a damage is taking place,
how much they're violating other things, these are types of things that
are going to motivate us whether to make this whether to do
this or to not do this. Okay? So that's framing it all
as a קנס. knas. Now let's take a look at the גמרא
Gemara as it turns to...
I'm going to take you back, I'm going to go מנסך menasech
your wine to עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. What? I'm going to I
you insulted me today, I'm going to go מנסך. menasech.
Yeah, I do understand I get it is a that is a
bizarre one. מדמע, Midame'a, you know, מערב m'arev, makes a lot more
sense in that context. Anyway, let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara Now the גמרא Gemara. turns to it's sort of already laid
out the conceptual framework implicitly working through the cases in the משנה,
Mishnah, but now it's going to directly address the conceptual framework. So
גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר חזקיה, Amar Chizkiyah,
דבר תורה devar Torah אחד שוגג ואחד מזיד חייב. echad shogeg ve'echad
mazid chayav. From a תורה Torah perspective whether שוגג shogeg or מזיד
mazid you if you damage somebody's, you know, stuff in this way,
really you'd have to pay. This isn't a קנס. knas. Really מעיקר
הדין me'ikar hadin you have to pay in all these cases. Okay?
אחד שוגג ואחד מזיד חייב. Echad shogeg ve'echad mazid chayav. מאי טעמא?
Mai ta'ama? היזק שאינו ניכר שמו היזק. Hezek she'eino nikar shemo hezek.
Even if it's not visible, it's still considered to be damages, right?
You did something to his object and it's worthless, that's considered you've
damaged his object. ומה טעם אמרו בשוגג פטור? Uma ta'am ameru beshogeg
patur? Why did they therefore if so if that's true, the חידוש
chiddush of the משנה Mishnah is not that you pay, which is
what we've been saying all along. The חידוש chiddush of the משנה
Mishnah is that you don't pay when you're שוגג. shogeg. So why
did they get you off the hook when you're שוגג? shogeg? I
mean, here's a guy you damaged his property you should pay, א
מזיק a mazik pays even בשוגג. beshogeg. So why did they say
בשוגג פטור? beshogeg patur?
כדי שיודיעו, Kedei sheyodi'o, so you should inform him, okay, which is
meaning he'll have no idea, he'll wind up eating תרומה טמאה, terumah
temei'ah, he'll wind up eating, you know, drinking יין נסך, yayin nesech,
he'll wind up eating תרומה terumah because you mixed it up, so
you're not going to tell him. Why should I tell him, I'm
just going to have to pay, right? It's like, you know, the
thing about I have to tell you once I was like backing
out of a car... the parking space in Manhattan, right? And a
little bit I like dinged the car behind me or whatever. So
like I left the, you know a note, right? Which is and
so, you know here's my whatever, here's my address, whatever, blah blah
blah. They contacted me, I paid them whatever it cost. Anyway, this
woman was like so effusive. Like, I can't believe it, somebody in
Manhattan you actually left a note, like you know, never happens, this
that, like you know. So it's like very easy, like hey, I
could get away with it, nobody's going to know, right? You know
just whatever. So here, right, you figure like, and and here at
least in that case the person knows that the car is dinged
and they gotta get it fixed, right? So there if when you're
informing you gotta pay and there's a יצר הרע Yetzer Hara not
to pay because if I inform, I'm going actually have to put
my hand in my pocket. Right here, so because of that יצר
הרע, Yetzer Hara, you're going to want to not tell the person
and and
then they're going to wind up doing all these ritual sins because
here the problem is it's not just, I mean it's not any
היזק שאינו ניכר, hezek she'eino nikar, I mean most normally the only
way you get היזק שאינו ניכר Hezek She'eino Nikar, is because you
change its halakhic status, right? In a normal world, in a non-religious
world, you don't have היזק שאינו ניכר. Hezek She'eino Nikar Right, you
know, you if there's a damage it's because it's something that's actually
you can see has changed with the object. Anyway, but
or maybe most of the time anyway.
So here in order to no
no no, like if you know like you have water and like
I you know see lead in it.
Yeah, alright, right. Right, so maybe there are scenarios, that's true. But
anyway, because it's שאינו ניכר, nikar. so here it's more important that
we that the guy be able to find out, rather than, you
know, that to say that that you know that the person will
have to pay, which will lead to a lot of cases the
person not informing, not paying, and the guy not finding out what
he needs to know. מיגו? Migo?
No.
מיגו Migo is a believability issue. Here, I mean, you know, what
you're sort of thinking is a similar, no, מיגו Migo is believe
me because of this because I could have done I could have
said this. Yeah, but this isn't a question about being believed, we
believe you that it was שוגג, Shogeg, but
שוגג Shogeg in this a similar
type of a structure, yeah. Okay. So anyway, so that's what he
says, that we do it in order, right, it's better to say
people are exempt in order that we find out what happened and
the person doesn't accidentally violate. Okay, כדי שיודעו. Kedei Sheyodi'o. אי הכי
I-hachi says the גמרא, Gemara אפילו במזיד נמי? afilu b'mezid nami? So
if it's במזיד b'mezid as well, we should we should
exempt the guy. Right, because I'm going to ruin you up and
I'll be מטמא metamei your thing and I'm not going to tell
you, right? So we should exempt the guy, so just so that
the person can find out. So the גמרא Gemara, says, no. התם
לאוזוקי קא מכוין אודועי לא מודי ליה? Hatam l'utze ka mechaven, adu'ei
lo modei lei? No, because when I'm trying to I'm מטמא metamei
your תרומה Trumah and I'm being mean and I'm doing it במזיד,
b'mezid, why am I doing it? Because I want you to sin
and get punished by God? Or do I want to make your
your grain worthless? Do I want to hurt you in עולם הזה,
Olam Hazeh, do I want to hurt you in עולם הבא? Olam
Haba? So the גמרא Gemara is assuming that if I'm doing it
במזיד b'mezid I want to hurt you in עולם הזה, Olam Hazeh,
not עולם הבא. Olam Haba. So therefore, I'm going to want you
to find out what I've done so that you'll know that you
can't eat your תרומה. Trumah. Right? Either I'll tell you directly, you
know, you're not going to be able to prove it but I'm
telling you buddy, I put your thing on תרומה, Trumah, right? Or
I'll do it in front of you and then, you know, but
again, but there's no evidence. It's a
he-said-he-you-know-he-said-this-type of a thing. He said she said or whatever it is.
So anyway, right? So so therefore, of course, I'm going to there's
going to I'm going to make you find out because I want
you to actually suffer that loss. Okay, so it's not a need
by במזיד, mezid, but it's a need by שוגג. shogeg. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
That's a דין din in שמים Shamayim case, I mean like you
know who who
bears the liability for that? Yeah, well I do because you're an
אונס, ones,
so I don't get any...
exactly. רב יוחנן אמר דבר תורה אחד שוגג ואחד מזיד פטור. Rav
Yochanan amar d'var Torah echad shogeg v'echad mezid patur. רב יוחנן Rav
Yochanan says what makes sense, what we've been essentially assuming by the
earlier גמרא. Gemara
Whether from a תורה Torah law whether שוגג shogeg or במזיד mezid
they're exempt. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? היזק שאינו ניכר לא שמיה היזק.
Hezek she'eino nikar lo shemeh hezek. It's not considered an active damage.
So why, I mean like... Alright, I'll get to that. מאי טעמא
אמרו במזיד חייב? Mai ta'ama amru b'mezid chayav? Why did they say
במזיד b'mezid you're חייב? chayav? שלא יהא כל אחד ואחד הולך ומטמא
טהרותיו של חבירו ואומר פטור אני, Shelo yei kol echad v'echad holeich
umetamei tehorotav shel chaveiro v'omeir patur ani, like we said before. So
if you're not allowed give people license to go ahead and willfully
damage somebody else's property. So by framing it like that and not
framing it in context of the ניזק, nizak, right this is what
we said before, like oh because this person suffered suffered a damage
and this other guy was at fault and we have to close
that gap. So by not framing it that way, framing it as
we need to stop you from these types of activities, it puts
it much more as a קנס knas and much less as a
רבני rabbinic דין. din. Now just to give you a similar comparison,
there's another whole discussion in the גמרא Gemara. about דינא דגרמי. Dina
d'garmi. Because if you want another example of of a way in
which I could damage you and be exempt. Here I did a
direct act, but if there's no visible mark of the act that
I did, there's no visible damage on the object. The other type
of way that I'm exempt is
that it's indirect. Okay, I caused a גרמא, grama, like I did
one thing which led to another thing, you know, I I don't
know, you know, I
opened up the gate which led to the cow going out, which
led to something else happening, you know led to him tripping and
breaking his leg or something like that or an example the גמרא
Gemara more extreme example is... I put some, I mixed a little
poison in your cow's feed, and I put the feed in front
of the cow, but I didn't actually directly do anything to the
cow, the cow came and ate the feed. So that's just גרמא,
grama, I'm פטור, pattur, okay? Now, there's a middle case which is
called גרמי. garmi. And גרמי garmi comes to close that gap and
it's called something which is more like it's more direct, it's not
as indirect. And there's whole questions of exactly what falls into the
category of גרמי, garmi, but it's not fully an act, but it's
not fully indirect and it's a middle case.
And the interesting debate in the, well
wait, the case of the poison is actually a גרמי garmi case.
Anyway, the discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim is how to conceptualize גרמי.
garmi. Do we conceptualize גרמי garmi as a type of a קנס,
knas, which is sort of taking its lead from this גמרא, Gemara
or do we conceptualize גרמי garmi as no, this is actually like
a loophole in the system that we have to close this hole?
Logically, this person deserves to be compensated, right? And we fundamentally start
from the fact that there's a justice that needs to be done.
You need to be paid for the damages, and he was at
fault that you're damaged, you suffered the damage, you need to be
paid. Just because of some technicality, we need to close that technicality,
close off that loophole. So if you focus on it that way,
it becomes an idea of like a rabbinic דין, din, not as
much of a קנס. knas. So I just want to sort of
give that as a counter example, that there are cases in which
technically you can damage somebody and not be חייב chayav מדאורייתא, mi'de'orayta,
and חז"ל Chazal came to address it, but they could address it
in one of two ways, right? This is a problem and we
have to punish people to stop them from doing it, or no,
this actually is a loophole, the person deserves to be compensated and
we have to therefore close that gap and create a type of
a rabbinic תשלום. tashlum. Okay, now the question about why, right, those
two different, that's clear, right? What those two different models are? Yes.
So if you put the poison in that food for the cow,
you're not חייב?
chayav? Right, at least you're not חייב chayav unless
you might be חייב chayav because of this middle category called גרמי.
garmi. But that's that question.
Is it like putting a stumbling block before?
Okay, so maybe you
transgressed something, but that doesn't mean that you did an act of
damages to have to pay,
you're not חייב chayav for damages.
Does that make sense to you by the way?
No, not so much, but okay. I mean that's a funny thing
when you learn בבא קמא Bava Kamma is that it's not just
any damage that you're responsible for, it's that you actually have to
do something that's defined as a formal act of מזיק. mazik. And
that's the other point that I wanted to make, which is I
think you know, when we understand like you sue a company because
they're negligent and it led to X amount of deaths or whatever,
and there's a general sense that if you're negligent and at fault,
you have to compensate. Whereas in הלכה, halacha, you need some more
direct connection than to be at fault. You might actually do an
act of damaging, or the middle case is my property went and
damaged, I was negligent with my property, my ox went and it
gored, but the fact that my property did it is still a
more something more concrete that connects me to the act than just
that I was negligent. Okay? So I mean negligence is חייב chayav
in a case of שומרים, shomrim, but not in a case of
מזיק. mazik. So
Michael is asking well how do I know that היזק שאינו ניכר
Hezek She'eino Nikar. is not היזק? hezek? And the answer is, you
know, I think you have to sort of start from the opposite
perspective. It's like the גמרא Gemara, gives examples about what is an
act of damage, right? It says like you know, the גמרא Gemara
says like what what
I mean not the גמרא, Gemara the תורה. Torah. Like what's the
case in the תורה? Torah? My שור shor gores your שור. shor.
I'm talking about what's the case of אדם המזיק adam hamazik in
the תורה? Torah?
What's the case in the תורה Torah of אדם המזיק? adam hamazik?
Well there's a case about יכה איש בעינו.
yakeh ish b'eyno.
Yeah, yeah, but that's חובל. chovel. I'm somehow I'm blanking on the
אדם המזיק adam hamazik case. Anyway, the point is all the scenarios
in the תורה Torah are very direct and very concrete, right? So
the question is, but of course it's not like damages are limited
to when it's my ox and your ox, it was my dog
and your dog, we wouldn't say oh you're פטור pattur because the
תורה Torah only talks about ox. Clearly you have to abstract and
generalize from those concrete cases. So I think that what the what
the חז"ל Chazal do, they don't actually quote a פסוק pasuk here
like they're debating whether it's שמי היזק shmei hezek and they're not
quoting פסוקים, pesukim, right? They're just sort of and I think that
the question is when you look at that case in the תורה,
Torah, what sort of do you feel are the necessary components that
the תורה Torah would require to say in that case you're liable?
So one aspect that חז"ל Chazal look at is they look at
the case of direct, it's a direct as opposed to indirect, and
it's you directly damaging doing an act against somebody else's person or
property. But the other thing is that maybe for something to be
considered damaged, it has to be visible. Now that seems strange to
us, right? But that's you know חז"ל Chazal often try to if
you think about it if it was like an act of a
מצוה, mitzvah, we would understand more some of these formal requirements. I
think that when we feel about meaning like הלכה halacha has all
these formal requirements, it's got to be a כזית בכדי אכילת פרס
kezayit b'khdei akhilat pras and you have to do it this way
and not that way, whatever. You know, I think when we deal
with damages we tend to think more less about act and more
about end result. You're to blame, this person's property is worthless, you
should compensate them. And I think that the חידוש chiddush of how
חז"ל Chazal looked at damages is that they define it as a
מעשה. מעשה maaseh maaseh. מעשה. ma'aseh. The same way if we were
dealing with a מצוה, mitzvah, we would understand it's not enough that
that כזית kezayis of מצה matzah got in my stomach, there's a
way in which it has to get done to be doing the
מצוה. mitzvah. So there's not enough that your property got damaged and
I was to blame, there's something that defines an act of damage
and one of the things seems to be that it's to be
considered to be ניכר. nikar, Okay, so I know it's a little
strange for us, meaning it's visible.
That's—What about intention? Why are we talking about intention with המזיק? hamazik?
Well, because the גמרא—Right. Gemara, Right. What?
Isn't there some punishment for that intention if it—if it actually happens
or—So
the גמרא Gemara talks about חייב בדיני שמיים, chayav bidinei shamayim, that,
you know,
you're—you're—you're liable up in heaven, but there's no—but—but—you know, so you might
have done a sin and you might be liable and רש"י Rashi
says חייב בדיני שמיים chayav bidinei shamayim might mean that if you
want things to be right between you and God, like you have
to pay the guy, not just that you'll be punished up there.
But is there again—but so nobody's saying that what you did is
okay, but the question is whether it's actual liable in damages. But
I do understand, it's—it's frustrating because they say like I'm to blame
and I did it willfully. Okay, but anyway that's the idea. So
let's take a look at the גמרא, Gemara הגמרא Gemara says like
this: רבי יוחנן אמר חזקיה אמר משמיה דבי מארי פטור מאי טעמא
היזק שאינו ניכר לא שמיה היזק מה טעם אמרו במזיד חייב שלא
יהא כל אחד ואחד הולך ומטמא טהרתו של חבירו ואומר פטור אני.
Rabbi Yochanan amar Chizkiyah amar mishmei d'vei Mari patur mai ta'ama hezek
she'eino nikar lo shemei hezek ma ta'am amru b'meizid chayav shelo yehei
kol echad v'echad holech u'metamei taharato shel chaveiro v'omer patur ani. Okay,
it's not.
Now we're going to try to prove it. Okay, הכהנים שפיגלו במקדש
מזידים חייבים. hakohanim shepiggulu b'mikdash meizidim chayavim.
We always—we always wonder in this.
So, right, there you go. If הכהנים, hakohanim, it's a next משנה.
mishnah. It's a משנה mishnah in זבחים Zevachim coming up. So it's
another example of היזק שאינו ניכר. hezek she'eino nikkar The כהן kohen
is שוחט shochting your קרבן, korban, but he's thinking that he's going
to eat it at the wrong time. So what that does is
it makes the קרבן korban טרייף. treif. Okay, so they made your
קרבן korban טרייף, treif, but you can't see how it's טרייף, treif,
it all looks כשר. kosher. Okay, so if they did it במזיד
b'meizid they're חייב. chayav. That's another example of היזק שאינו ניכר. hezek
she'eino nikar. הגמרא Gemara says ותני עלה מפני תיקון העולם. v'tanya ala
mipnei tikkun ha'olam. So that sounds like the תיקון העולם tikkun ha'olam
is to make them pay, because that משנה mishnah doesn't say שוגג
פטור, shogeg patur, it just says מזיד חייב meizid chayav and מזיד
חייב מפני תיקון העולם meizid chayav mipnei tikkun ha'olam sounds like the
תיקון העולם tikkun ha'olam is to make them pay, sounds like רבי
יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
So הגמרא Gemara says ואי אמרת
היזק שאינו ניכר שמיה היזק, v'i amart hezek she'eino nikar shemei hezek,
if you say that fundamentally you're חייב chayav and the תקנה takanah
was to make you פטור, patur, היי שוגג פטורים מפני תיקון העולם
איבעי ליה, hei shogeg peturim mipnei tikkun ha'olam ibei lei, it should
have said you're exempt when you do it בשוגג b'shogeg because of
תיקון העולם, tikkun ha'olam, but it's not what it said. It said
you're חייב chayav when you do it במזיד b'meizid because of תיקון
העולם. tikkun ha'olam. Makes it clear that the baseline is that you're
exempt. So הגמרא Gemara says no, הכי נמי קאמר, hachi nami ka'amar,
that's what it means. מזידים חייבים, meizidim chayavim, you're חייב chayav במזיד,
b'meizid, implicitly שוגגים פטורים, shogegim peturim, we're going to exempt you when
you're שוגג, shogeg, why? מפני תיקון העולם. mipnei tikkun ha'olam. והתיקון העולם
v'hatikkun ha'olam goes on the implicit part of the statement, not the
explicit. Fine, whatever. מתיב רב יוסף, metiv Rav Yosef, he asks and
answers it. העושה מלאכה במי חטאת ובפרת חטאת פטור מדיני אדם וחייב
בדיני שמיים. ha'oseh melachah b'mei chatas u'v'faras chatas patur midinei adam v'chayav
bidinei shamayim. If you go ahead and you take water of פרה
אדומה parah adumah that the ashes of the פרה אדומה parah adumah
were mixed in, or you take the cows, the red cow while
it's still alive, and you do מלאכה melachah with them. Okay, you
make your cow plow a furrow, you use the water to—in a
scale to weigh against some other object. In those types of things
you now have made it invalid for use of פרה אדומה. parah
adumah. The פרה parah is invalid, the water is invalid.
Okay, and היזק שאינו ניכר hezek she'eino nikar.
possible. Right, so that's היזק שאינו ניכר. hezek she'eino nikar So again,
you're חייב chayav במזיד b'meizid and שוגג shogeg you're פטור, patur,
פטור מדיני אדם, patur midinei adam, well actually this is interesting, this
doesn't say מזיד meizid or שוגג, shogeg, okay, וחייב בדיני שמיים. v'chayav
bidinei shamayim. So it's not clear, like why didn't they—like is this
talking about a case of שוגג? shogeg? Is this talking about a
case of מזיד? meizid? What happened to the מזיד—שוגג distinction? That's not
so clear, maybe again, maybe we didn't make a קנס knas in
this case. What is interesting also is that you are חייב בדיני
שמיים, chayav bidinei shamayim, right? So that's an important thing to address,
David's concern and everybody's concern about where's the justice in this. Okay,
so I mean—and David, if you want to see like רש"י Rashi
says חייב בדיני שמיים, chayav bidinei shamayim, רש"י Rashi says פורענות לשלם
לרשעים שנתכווין להפסיד את ישראל. puranus l'shalem l'rasha'im sheniskavein l'hafsid es Yisrael.
Okay, so you're going to get punished because you intentionally damaged somebody.
And now רש"י Rashi says נתכווין, niskavein, so רש"י Rashi makes it
actually a case of מזיד, meizid which is interesting. But anyway, but
some say that חייב בדיני שמיים, chayav bidinei shamayim, another רש"י Rashi
in another גמרא, Gemara, basically says that you have some obligation to
this other person, just the court is not going to be able
to force you to pay. But there is some sense of a
moral obligation to this person, but just the court can't force you.
Anyway, that's what you have here, and it's not distinguishing here מזיד
meizid, and שוגג, shogeg but what is clear is that the baseline
is that you're exempt. So again, it's another proof that היזק שאינו
ניכר לא שמיה היזק, hezek she'eino nikar lo shemei hezek, the baseline
is that you're exempt. So הגמרא Gemara says ואי אמרת היזק שאינו
ניכר שמיה היזק בדיני אדם נמי ליחייב, v'i amart hezek she'eino nikar
shemei hezek bidinei adam nami litchayev, why are you also not חייב
chayav בדיני אדם? bidinei adam? So הגמרא Gemara says הוא מותיב לה
והוא מפרק לה, hu motiv lah v'hu mefarek lah, he asked it
and he answered it. פרה שהכניסה לרבקה על מנת שתנק ותדוש. parah
shehichnisah l'rivkah al m'nas shetinak v'tadush. Basically you had this calf go
into a pen where other cows were, and its mother was there,
and you wanted it to suckle from the mother, and also while
it was in the pen there was like grain on the floor
of the pen and you wanted it to thresh the grain.
Okay, which therefore what? So רש"י Rashi says— מחמת מחשבתו שנתכוין שתדוש
וגרמא בנזיקין פטור. machmat machshavto she'nitkavein she'tadush ve'grama benizikin patur. Yeah. Oh,
okay.
It's all פרה אדומה.
Para Aduma. Okay, so here's what רש"י Rashi says. This is not
only היזק שאינו ניכר. hezek she'eino nikar. Remember I said the one
point is the end result, the object gets visibly damaged. But the
other point is that I directly do the act or did I
indirectly do the act. So רש"י Rashi says we're going to turn
this into a case where the problem isn't that the damage wasn't
visible, there's a problem is that you didn't directly do it. Why
did I not directly do it? Because only did it was my
thoughts. I didn't do it with my actions. How did you do
it with your thoughts? Well, if it's going into nurse from the
mother, then that doesn't make it פסול, pasul, that's not going in
for עבודה. avodah. It also is threshing on the grain, but that's
not defined as עבודה avodah unless my intention is that it actually
thresh the grain, then it's considered like it's doing an עבודה. avodah.
Okay, so רש"י Rashi says in this case what makes it a
היזק hezek is your thoughts. And that's why you're exempt because you
didn't really do an action, not just because the result wasn't ניכר,
nikar but because you didn't really do an action.
Now, and how about the מי חטאת ששקל בהן משקלות? mei chatat
sheshakal ben mishkalot? That you used it to weigh in a balance.
So that's not clear why that's exempt. Isn't that using it to
do מלאכה? melakhah? So the גמרא Gemara, says אמר רבא מי חטאת
ששקל בהן משקלות כשרה. Amar Rava mei chatat sheshakal ben mishkalot kesherah.
So actually it'd be the other way, which says one minute, like
isn't that, that's not a מלאכה melakhah if you just used it
as a counterbalance. So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא הא בגופן
הא בכנגדן. lo kashya ha begufan ha bichenegdan.
Depends how were you using it to weigh. If you put it
in a balance and you put one thing in one side of
the balance and the other in the other, so that's not considered
like you're doing a
מלאכה melakhah with them somehow. If however you put something in to
the water and you're measuring something volume by the water displacement, then
you're really directly using it as a form of measuring, that's considered
a מלאכה. melakhah. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says so we must be talking about a case of בגופן,
begufan, right? Because you invalidated the מי חטאת. mei chatat. So if
that's true we're back to the question, why aren't you paying? Right
is everybody with me? You're not paying in the case that I
used the מי חטאת mei chatat and the question is doesn't that
show you that היזק שאינו ניכר לא שמיה היזק? hezek she'eno nikar
lo shemeh hezek? And the first answer is well by the case
of the cow itself, it was done by your thoughts, it wasn't
really direct action. Okay, but the case of using the water, if
you're actually the case that you made it invalid is you put
something in the water and you did water displacement, how is that
not an actual action? It's not ניכר nikar, but it's an action.
So the גמרא Gemara says מעשה קא עביד בהו היזק שאינו ניכר
שמיה היזק בדיני אדם נמי ליחייב? ma'aseh ka avid behu hezek she'eno
nikar shemeh hezek bedini adam nami lechayev? So you should be חייב.
chayav. Who cares right? So the fact that you're exempt even though
you did an action shows that the fact that it's not visible
is enough to make you exempt. גמרא Gemara says אלא אידי ואידי
בכנגדן. ela idi ve'idi bekenegdan.
Fine. Both cases you're using it as a counterbalance. So then what's
the difference whether you're חייב chayav or not? ולא קשיא הא דאסח
דעתיה הא דלא אסח דעתיה. velo kashya ha de'asach da'ateh ha de'lo
asach da'ateh. When you use it as a counterbalance, that's not considered
a מלאכה. melakhah. I didn't directly use the object. Okay. So what
makes it invalid when I use it as a counterbalance? What makes
it invalid is, is that I was not paying full attention to
the object. And actually היסח הדעת, hesach hada'at, I got distracted. And
actually by מי חטאת, mei chatat, even something as simple as היסח
הדעת, hesach hada'at, not being focused on protecting it, is enough to
invalidate it. So what it's similar to the other case, what really
invalidates it in that case is not that I did מלאכה, melakhah,
מלאכה melakhah was just the proximate cause. What really invalidates is since
I was thinking for a moment about weighing you know weighing my
grain and I was using this to weigh my grain and I
wasn't completely focused on the מי חטאת, mei chatat, I invalidated the
מי חטאת mei chatat by being distracted. And therefore, what's the act
of היזק hezek here? The act of היזק hezek was something done
through my דעת, da'at, through lack of my דעת. da'at. So the
problem here was not that it wasn't ניכר, nikar, the problem here
was was that it wasn't a physical action done, right? So again,
the simple sense of this is the reason you're exempt by this
case of the חטאת chatat is because the end result is not
ניכר, nikar. is not visible, right? Because that's a simple sense, you
can't see the damage done. And the answer is no, we're going
to make it a case where it's not just that it wasn't
visible, but that it wasn't even a physical action, it was done
by thought or by absence of thought because you wanted the cow
to thresh in your mind, that defines it as an act of
מלאכה melakhah because you were distracted from paying attention to the water,
that defines it as becoming פסול. pasul. So it's because of the
thought that it was done through thought or absence of thought that
it was a lack of an action, but it wasn't because it
was a lack of ניכר.
We don't know what the
default is, whether היזק שאינו ניכר שמיה היזק. hezek she'eno nikar shemeh
hezek. We don't know what the default is. And we somehow fell
significantly behind, I think I spent too much time explaining things.